<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation concerning the particulars of the rebellion lately raised in Muscovy by Stenko Razin its rise, progress, and stop : together with the manner of taking that rebel, the sentence of death passed upon him, and the execution of the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3393</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11880901</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11880901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50330</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58415)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50330)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 508:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation concerning the particulars of the rebellion lately raised in Muscovy by Stenko Razin its rise, progress, and stop : together with the manner of taking that rebel, the sentence of death passed upon him, and the execution of the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p. : fold. ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Newcomb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] In the Savoy :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The relation dated, p. 18: Arch-Angel, Sept. 23, 1671 on board of the ship, the Queen Esther.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Razin, Stepan Timofeevich, d. 1671.</term>
               <term>Cossacks.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:50330:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50330:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>prisoner flanked by two guards with axes on a cart drawn by three horses, whose reins are held by a man wielding a whip; at lower left, another prisoner, his brother, chained to back of cart by the neck; at upper right, inset portrait of the rebel Stepan Razin</figDesc>
                  <p>RAZIN the Rebell</p>
                  <p>his Brother</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50330:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50330:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION Concerning the Particulars of the REBELLION Lately raiſed in MUSCOVY BY Stenko Razin; Its Riſe, Progreſs, and Stop; together with the manner of taking that REBEL, the Sentence of Death paſſed upon him, and the Execution of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY:</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Newcomb.</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50330:4"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50330:4"/>
            <head>A RELATION Concerning the Particulars of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion lately raiſed in <hi>Muſcovy</hi> by <hi>Stenko Razin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two ſorts of <hi>Coſacks,</hi> ſome are call'd <hi>Saporogsky,</hi> and others <hi>Donsky.</hi> The former do from antient times belong to the Dominions of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and have their ordinary abode in the Iſles of the River <hi>Boryſthenes</hi> or <hi>Nieper.</hi> At a good diſtance from the Town <hi>Kiof,</hi> in the ſame River, is to be found a Rock, from which the Water falling with great violence, maketh above Fifty Iſles; and this Rock, whence the Water falls, is called <hi>Poroch,</hi> and giveth to thoſe <hi>Coſacks,</hi> which are ſeated in thoſe Iſles that lie behinde the <hi>Poroch,</hi> the name of <hi>Saporogsky.</hi> Their buſineſs is, to be watchful againſt the Incurſions of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and other enemies of the Kingdom of <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Name of <hi>Coſack</hi> is ſaid to be derived from the <hi>Sclavonian</hi> word <hi>Coſa,</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>Spirit;</hi> and it is thought, that that name was given to that people by reaſon of their Agility or Nimbleneſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Donsky-Coſacks</hi> are thoſe that have their habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon the famous River <hi>Don,</hi> antiently called
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50330:5"/>
               <hi>Tanais,</hi> and belong to the Czar or Emperor of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> to whom they yield a voluntary, rather than a compelled obedience. They are by the ſaid Czar endowed with many Priviledges, enjoying their own Laws, and chuſing their own Governor. They have ſo great Priviledges, that if any Slave run away from a <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Nobleman or other great Perſon, and come unto theſe <hi>Coſacks,</hi> the Proprietors looſe their claim to them.</p>
            <p>Of theſe <hi>Donsky-Coſacks</hi> was <hi>Stenko Razin,</hi> the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that four years ſince roſe up in Rebellion againſt the great Czar <hi>Alexis Michalowitz.</hi> The reaſon or rather pretence of that Inſurrection was, the death of the ſaid <hi>Razin</hi>'s Brother, inflicted by the Bojar <hi>Kneas Jurge Dolgeroek.</hi> For in the year 1665. he was with an Army in the Field, about the Town <hi>Kiof,</hi> againſt the <hi>Polanders,</hi> having under him, among others, a Troup of <hi>Donsky-Coſacks.</hi> Autumn being come in, and that Troup eſteeming to have done good ſervice againſt the enemy, deſired to be diſmiſſed by the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander <hi>Dolgeroek,</hi> who poſſibly ſtanding yet in need of their ſervice, would not conſent to it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon theſe <hi>Coſacks,</hi> unwilling to hearken to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their General; but following the perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and example of their chief Officer, which was the Brother of <hi>Stenko Razin,</hi> did disband, and went every one to his home. <hi>Dolgeroek</hi> being extreamly offended thereat, gave order, that this Ring-Leader ſhould be taken; which being done, he commanded him preſently to be hanged.</p>
            <p>This is the cauſe, pretended by <hi>Razin,</hi> when he was upon the Rack, of his raiſing this Rebellion, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the death of his Brother, innocently executed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50330:5"/>as he underſtood it. But that this was but a meer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, is ſufficiently apparent, in regard that this Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was made not onely againſt the Czar, but alſo againſt the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> from whom he never could alledge to have received any injury. So that nothing but his malicious, and rebellious temper, hath impel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to this infamous undertaking.</p>
            <p>The beginning of his villanous attempt was, his robbery upon the River <hi>Volga, An.</hi> 1667, where he took ſeveral great Boats laden with Commodities, belonging partly to Cloiſters and Eccleſiaſticks, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to private Merchants of <hi>Jereſlaf, Wologda,</hi> and other places. Thence he went to the Town <hi>Jayck,</hi> which he took by force, aſſiſted by his <hi>Coſacks.</hi> Soon after he proceeded to the <hi>Caſpian Sea;</hi> and from thence he returned to the <hi>Volga,</hi> where he did great miſchief in giving interruption to Fiſhing, and in ruining many Houſes. Thence he marched to the Town <hi>Teock,</hi> and further to the Frontiers of <hi>Perſia,</hi> where he did great damage to the Subjects, both of the great Czar of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> and the Chach of <hi>Perſia.</hi> The Inhabitants of a certain ſmall <hi>Perſian</hi> Town, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed of his approach, betook themſelves to a Neighboring Fort for ſecurity. Whereupon <hi>Stenko</hi> ſent them word, that they had no reaſon to fear, and invited them to return, aſſuring them, That he and his Men were not come to do them any hurt, but for Money to buy Proviſion, and other Neceſſaries for his Troups. They came back with great confidence to their Town, and opened their Shops, where <hi>Stenko</hi> and his Soldiers bought what they needed, and paid for what they bought that time; but afterwards he gave a ſign to his <hi>Coſacks,</hi> that paſſing over the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50330:6"/>when he ſhould put his Cap into a certain poſture, they ſhould fall upon and kill all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; which was executed accordingly, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſeveral other places upon the Borders of <hi>Perſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſtop theſe cruel actions, the <hi>Kneas Jwan Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newitz,</hi> then Waywode or Governor of <hi>Aſtracan</hi> ſent ſome Troups againſt him. Whereupon <hi>Stenko,</hi> finding himſelf too weak, and apprehending a bad iſſue, asked pardon; to which, the ſaid Governor returned this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That if he would deſiſt from his violence and robbery, he doubted not but the great Czar would ſhew him Mercy. He came with his companions to <hi>Astracan,</hi> almoſt all ſick and ſwelled, becauſe having been a little before, upon a certain Iſland in the <hi>Caſpian Sea,</hi> beſet by the <hi>Perſians,</hi> they had been neceſſitated to drink Salt-water. And he at length received par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don from the Czar for his crimes, and promiſed, That he and his Company would henceforth ſerve him with all faithfulneſs, nor exerciſe any robbery on the <hi>Volga,</hi> or the <hi>Caſpian Sea,</hi> or elſwhere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stenko</hi> being recovered, ſhewed his generoſity to the Inhabitants of <hi>Astracan.</hi> For as he was walking thorough the Streets, he ſcattered among the people ſtore of Ducats and other Coyn he had robbed, and thereby was applauded by all; which then ſufficiently manifeſted his aim. And ſo he, with his aſſociates, went away to their own Countrey about the River <hi>Don;</hi> where he began to act afreſh his villainy in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Matters, driving away many Prieſts, and hindring Divine Service, and intruding himſelf into Church affairs. For a pattern of the glorious Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which this <hi>Coſack-Pope</hi> introduced, take this,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50330:6"/>that inſtead of the uſual Ceremonies of Marriage per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Prieſts in <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> he made the contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed couple to goe ſeveral times round about a Tree dancing, and thus they were married after <hi>Stenko</hi>'s mode. He alſo caſt out blaſphemous words againſt the Saviour of the World; and ſcrupled not forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to break that Oath of Fidelity, which a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had ſworn to the Great Czar; and put to death divers ancient Coſſacks, that had more integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than to combine with him in his rebellion. The like he acted upon the Waywode of the ſame place, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that had been ſent by the Czar with Letters of Grace and Pardon, and others.</p>
            <p>From the River <hi>Don</hi> he return'd to the <hi>Volga,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his Aſſociats, and came to the Town <hi>Saret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> where he perſwaded the Inhabitants, that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Great Czar was at hand to put them all to death; whereas on the contrary that Army was come to aſſiſt them againſt <hi>Stenko:</hi> and thus the Town was ſurrendred to him; and he having made his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, killed the Commander and all the Citizens that refuſed to joyn with him. He marched out again to meet the Army of the Czar; which he defeated, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and putting to death the General, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. He took alſo the Town <hi>Sionejaer;</hi> where he put to the Sword the Governour, all the Officers, and many Muſcovian ſoldiers.</p>
            <p>Thence he marched to the City of <hi>Aſtracan,</hi> ſeated at the mouth of the River <hi>Volga,</hi> not far from the <hi>Caſpian Sea,</hi> walled about, and having in compaſs more than two miles. The Suburbs lying round about it, are moſt of them bare, and expoſed to the incurſion of any Enemy. Some years ſince was this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50330:7"/>Town poſſeſſed by the Tartars, from whom it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Czar <hi>Jwan Waſelowitz, An.</hi> 1553. About it grows no Grain at all, but 'tis provided from above. It is rich chiefly in Salt and Fiſh; the <hi>Caſpian Sea</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the people, living on that ſhore, with ſtore of Salt water, of which they make whole mountains of Salt. And the <hi>Volga</hi> about <hi>Aſtracan</hi> abounds in Fiſh above all Rivers. There they catch thoſe great Fiſhes, <hi>Oſſotrina, Belouga,</hi> ſome of the latter being three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoms long, one of which can hardly be carried by thirty men. In <hi>Aſtracan</hi> is great Commerce, managed by forrain Nations, Perſians, Indians, Boucharen, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians, and others, it hath for its ordinary Gariſon Twelve thouſand Soldiers. <hi>Stenko Razin</hi> coming to this City, ſent ſome of his Coſſacks into it, to ſtirre up the Soldiers againſt the Governor; which wrought ſo well, that it was concluded the Town ſhould be deliver'd to him, and he received into it: which was executed according to his wiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kneas Jwan Semenof Proſorofskie,</hi> being at Church, in the midſt of Divine Service was thence pull'd away, and made to goe up that high ſquare Steeple, which ſtands in the midſt of the Caſtle of <hi>Aſtracan,</hi> for a Beacon to direct thoſe that Navigate the <hi>Caſpian Sea,</hi> or travel in the vaſt and little frequented fields called <hi>Steep.</hi> From this Steeple the ſaid Governor was caſt down head-long. 'Tis ſaid, that <hi>Stenko</hi> a little before whiſper'd him ſomething in his ear, at which he ſhook his head, being doubtleſs tempted by this Traytor to take his part, which the <hi>Kneas</hi> refuſing to doe, was forced to make this high and Tragical leap.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stenko Razin</hi> immediately hereupon committed great ſlaughter and robbing. The Brother of the Governor,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50330:7"/>and many Noble-men and others, that would not come in to him, he put to the ſword, as alſo many Dutch and other Officers, and ſome Holland Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which though they run into the <hi>Caſpian Sea,</hi> yet are ſaid to have been fetcht back and killed. Colonel <hi>Thomas Bely,</hi> and Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>Jacob Wanderow,</hi> and others, were put to the Sword, being in Arms up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the walls of the Town. The Churches, Cloiſters, and the Houſes of the richeſt Citizens were plunder'd; the Writings of the Chancery burnt, the Czar's Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Kingdom of <hi>Aſtracan</hi> carried away, many Merchants ſtrangers, being there at that time, as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Indians, Turks, Arminians, and others, were put to death with the reſt: both the Sons of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour <hi>Proſorofskie</hi> he cauſed to be hung up by the Legs upon the Walls of the Town, and to be taken down again, putting one of them, after much torture, to death, and cauſing the other to be beaten half dead, and ſo carried to the Metropolitan. His Lady and Daughters he delivered to the Soldiers, his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to take them for their Wives, or, if they pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to abuſe them. This taking of <hi>Aſtracan</hi> happen'd <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 28. 1670.</p>
            <p>After this, <hi>Stenko</hi> marched to <hi>Tzaretſa,</hi> and thence to <hi>Tzarataf,</hi> which were alſo deliver'd to him, and the Governors of them put to death, together with many Noble men; and the Treaſure carried away.</p>
            <p>The like happen'd to the Town <hi>Tzamatof;</hi> from whence <hi>Stenko</hi> went to the Town <hi>Simbierske,</hi> which he beſieged, took by ſtorm, and burnt to aſhes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had loſt a great part of his Coſſacks before the Caſtle of that place. The Governor of it was the Lord
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50330:8"/>
               <hi>Jwan Bochdaenwitz Micoſlafsky,</hi> who with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courage defended it againſt this Traytor: ſo that <hi>Stenko,</hi> conquerour of all the places upon the <hi>Volga,</hi> was ſtop'd here from going further; without which he was reſolved to have marched to the Royal City <hi>Caſan,</hi> not far diſtant from <hi>Simbierske.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although <hi>Stenko</hi> was now hindred to paſs further, as being beaten, and wounded himſelf, inſomuch that he was conſtrained to return to his <hi>Aſtracan</hi>-Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet did he much miſchief in <hi>Ruſſia</hi> by his Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who here and there ſtirr'd up the people to inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. In <hi>Galitz</hi> the fire began, but was ſoon quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. About the Town <hi>Oeſtiga</hi> ſome of thoſe Emiſſaries were caught, taken, and hanged. Every where he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Liberty, and a redemption from the Yoak (ſo he call'd it) of the <hi>Bojars</hi> or Nobles, which he ſaid were the oppreſſors of the Countrey; In <hi>Mosko</hi> it ſelf, men began to ſpeak openly in his praiſe, as if he were a perſon that ſought the publick good and the liberty of the people; for which cauſe the Great Czar was neceſſitated to make a publick example of ſome, to deterr the reſt.</p>
            <p>A certain aged man being asked, what ſhould be done in caſe that <hi>Stenko</hi> ſhould approach to the City of <hi>Mosko,</hi> anſwered, that the people ſhould goe and meet him with Bread and Salt, which among the Ruſſians is a token of Love and Friendſhip. For which this man was taken and hanged.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time, there was brought into the ſame City, one of the principal Aſſociats of <hi>Stenko,</hi> that had undertaken to debauch the people up and down in the Countrey from their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50330:8"/>but he had his due reward; for one of his Arms, and one of his Legs were cut off, and he preſently hanged on the Gallows.</p>
            <p>All ſorts of imaginable miſchievous devices were ſet on foot by <hi>Stenko</hi> to ruine the Ruſſian Empire, and to ſeduce the common people.</p>
            <p>Amongſt other Artifices, he had prepared two ſhips, one of which was lined within round about with Red Velvet; and he gave out, that in it was the Lord <hi>Czarawitz,</hi> of Glorious memory, <hi>Alexis Alexewitz,</hi> the Great Czar's eldeſt Son; who yet in the year 1670. on the 17th of <hi>January</hi> in the preſence of his Father, in the Pallace of <hi>Mosko,</hi> departed this life, and the next day was buried in the Metropolitan Church of <hi>S. Michel. Stenko</hi> boldly pretended, that this Prince was yet alive, and with him. And to colour this lye the better, he kept in the ſaid ſhip a Youth of about 16 years of age, deſcended of one of the <hi>Peregorsky Circaſſian</hi> Princes, whom <hi>Stenko</hi> in his former depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations had taken priſoner: which young Prince hath received the Great Czar's pardon, becauſe he was compelled to act ſuch a perſon; and he is ſtill in <hi>Mosko,</hi> at the houſe of <hi>Kneas Jacob Codonietewitz</hi> a <hi>Circaſſian.</hi> And to drive on theſe devices, he ſpred abroad, that this Lord <hi>Czarawitz</hi> had made an eſcape from the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands of the Bojars and great Lords, and taken his refuge to him; adding, that he, <hi>Stenko,</hi> was come by order of the Great Czar to put to death all the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jars, Nobles, Senators, and other great ones, (that were too near to his Majeſty,) as Enemies and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of their Countrey. By theſe baſe practiſes invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and puſh't on by <hi>Stenko,</hi> the ignorant people was inflamed to fight furiouſly, and thoſe of them that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50330:9"/>were taken priſoners underwent death with a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful reſolution, as being poſſeſſed with the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of dying for a good cauſe.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Smolensko</hi> was hanged a certain perſon, who ſaid, that he died upon having ſeen with <hi>Stenko</hi> the Prince <hi>Czarawitz,</hi> whereas he ſaw but a counterfeit one.</p>
            <p>The other ſhip, that <hi>Stenko</hi> had, was lined with Black Velvet, and he gave out, that there was in it the late Patriarch <hi>Nikow,</hi> who in the year 1666. was, upon the Condemnation paſſed by the Patriarchs of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and of <hi>Antioch,</hi> by his Majeſty, the Great Czar, depoſed from his Dignity, and ſent to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of <hi>Belooſer,</hi> where he is yet at this day.</p>
            <p>By theſe Arts <hi>Stenko</hi> had ſo far advanced his deſign that the whole Tract of Land about the <hi>Volga</hi> and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up into the Countrey was engaged in this rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, as far as to the Towns <hi>Accateur</hi> and <hi>Arſa:</hi> And the number of the Rebels was augmented to two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand, and part of the <hi>Czerniſche Tartars,</hi> and all the Ruffian Countrey-men living in this Tract, and belonging to Muſcovian Lords, roſe up againſt their Governors killing and hanging them; and the fire of this Rebellion gained at length ſo much ground, that it began to burn not above twelve miles from <hi>Mosko</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Great Czar raiſed a great Army, and under the conduct of the Noble <hi>Kneas Jurge Alexewitz Dolgeroek</hi> ſent it, about the end of <hi>September,</hi> againſt the Enemy, of whom he met a party of Fifteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, who though they fought reſolutely and rallied three times, yet were at length beaten and put to ſlight, very many remaining dead upon the place,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50330:9"/>and a great number being taken, who were immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately executed. Six Field pieces fell into the hands of <hi>Dolgeroek;</hi> who encamped under the Town <hi>Arſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> where he exerciſed ſevere judgment upon theſe Rebels. The place was terrible to behold, and had the reſemblance of the Suburbs of Hell. Round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it were Gallows, each of which was loaded with Forty or fifty Men. In another place lay many Beheaded and covered with Blood. Here and there ſtood ſome impaled, whereof not a few lived unto the third day, and were heard to ſpeak. Within the ſpace of Three Moneths, there were by the Hands of Executioners put to death Eleven thouſand Men, in a legal way, upon the hearing of Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dolgeroek</hi> himſelf remaining upon the place of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſent his Army out by Parties, that found out, defeated, and diſperſed <hi>Stenko</hi>'s forces. It was of great importance to <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> and a great Mercy of God, that the Rebels lay here and there divided; as alſo, that they could not agree amongſt themſelves, about the Supream Command. For if this power of the Rebels, conſiſting of Two hundred thouſand Men, had been united and unanimous, it would have been difficult for the Forces of the Czar to have reſiſted and maſtered the ſame.</p>
            <p>The <hi>German</hi> Officers were highly applauded by His Majeſty, for having acquitted themſelves ſo well in leading on their Men. The moſt reſolute of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, were thoſe of the ſmall Towns of <hi>Lisko</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasko,</hi> who had more than once attempted to take by ſtorm the Cloiſter of <hi>Macariof,</hi> and loſt a great number of Men before it, taking it at laſt by the treachery of a Jew, and putting to death all the Monks that were
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50330:10"/>found in it, and carrying away a rich prey, becauſe the people living thereabout had carried their Goods thither for ſecurity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Morasko</hi> held out; but thoſe of <hi>Lisko</hi> rendred themſelves in good time, and delivered Thirty of the Rebellious <hi>Coſacks,</hi> together with a Nephew of <hi>Stenko Razin,</hi> and ſo they were pardoned.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the Priſoners, there was brought to <hi>Kneas Jurge Dolgeroek</hi> a Nun in Man's habit, put over her Monaſtical dreſs. This Nun had commanded Seven thouſand Men, and done bravely in this War, till ſhe was taken priſoner. There appeared not any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in her, nor any fear of death, when the Sentence of being Burnt alive was pronounced againſt her. Amongſt the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> the deſerting of a Monaſtery, is eſteemed a black and capital crime. A little before ſhe died, ſhe wiſhed that many more had behaved themſelves, and fought as couragiouſly as ſhe had done; that then certainly <hi>Kneas Jurge</hi> would have found his beſt ſafety in his heels.</p>
            <p>Being now to die, ſhe ſigned herſelf after the <hi>Ruſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> manner, with the croſs on her forehead and breſt, and ſo laid her ſelf quietly down upon the Pile, and was burnt to Aſhes.</p>
            <p>There was alſo brought to Judgment, one of <hi>Stenko Razin</hi>'s Confederates, and his beſt Counſellor, who had been his right hand. His Arms and Legs were cut off, and ſo he was Beheaded and Hanged.</p>
            <p>The Priſoners were commonly put upon the Rack, and being examined, what they deſigned in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; they anſwered, That they intended for <hi>Moſco,</hi> and would have the lives of the Nobles, and other great ones, Their word was <hi>Not'ſchay,</hi> that is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50330:10"/>to ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexpected;</hi> intimating, That the Czarawitz <hi>Alexis Alexewitz</hi> was come as it were from Heaven, beſides their expectation.</p>
            <p>Thus hath <hi>Kneas Jurge Dolgeroek</hi> in the ſpace of Three Moneths made an end of this Rebellion, in the Quarters about the River <hi>Don;</hi> but in other places the Fire was not yet extinguiſhed, when the Czar called him back with his Army.</p>
            <p>Mean time <hi>Kneas Conſtantine Czarbatof</hi> was by His Majeſty commanded to march towards <hi>Taneboef,</hi> there to ſubdue the Rebels of thoſe parts; which alſo by the aſſiſtance of God was effected. So that all the Diſquieted and Rebellious Countreys have been, by Hanging, Burning, Beheading, Slaughtering (beſides the Eleven thouſand Executed by the Hands of Hangmen,) and by killing in the Field above an Hundred thouſand Men, reduced to their former obedience.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Stenko Razin;</hi> after that he had been routed about <hi>Simbierske,</hi> and was retired down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, he choſe a freer Air for his abode, and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a while in the Wilderneſs of <hi>Steep,</hi> leaving to one of his Confederates, call'd <hi>Sjorte-Ous,</hi> that is the <hi>Divels Knuckle,</hi> the command of <hi>Aſtracan: Stenko</hi> in the mean time, wandring up and down, until at length by the Captain <hi>Cornelius Jacolowitz,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Donsky-Coſacks</hi> that had remained faithful to the Czar, he was ſecured and brought into <hi>Moſco.</hi> This <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Jacolowitz</hi> was God-father to <hi>Stenko,</hi> and always honored by him, as if he had been his Father; whence he never in the leaſt imagined, that that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould contrive any miſchief againſt him. But he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50330:11"/>that was ſo perfidious to his Prince, deſerved no better recompence.</p>
            <p>He was laid hold on about <hi>Tzarietza,</hi> and carried that long way of Two hundred Miles to <hi>Moſco,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained all along with the hopes, that he ſhould ſpeak with the Great Czar himſelf, and before him, by word of Mouth, plead his own cauſe, he always imagining, that he had many things to ſay, very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant for the Czar to know.</p>
            <p>His Brother <hi>Frolko</hi> was extreamly ſad on the way, and, it ſeems, of a better nature than <hi>Stenko,</hi> whom he charged with all he had done. And <hi>Stenko</hi> ſeeing his Brother at a certain time more than uſually troubled, comforted him by repreſenting, that coming into the City of <hi>Moſco,</hi> they ſhould receive great honor, thouſands of people, and the greateſt of the Land being (doubtleſs) ready to meet, and to ſee them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stenko</hi> coming within a mile of <hi>Moſco,</hi> the Waggon met him that had been made to bring him into the City according to his deſerts. In the hind-part of it was erected the Gallows; himſelf was ſtripped of his Silken habit, which he had worn hitherto, and an old ragged Sute put upon him; and ſo he was placed in the Waggon under the Gallows, with an Iron-Chain about his Neck, faſtned to the top of the ſame. Both his hands were locked faſt to the Side-beams of the Gallows, and his Legs divaricated. His Brother <hi>Frolko</hi> was with an Iron-Chain faſtned to the Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and went a foot on the ſide of it.</p>
            <p>Thus entred <hi>Stenko</hi> with his Brother into the City of <hi>Moſco,</hi> Thouſands of People, of great and mean condition, beholding them, and ſo fulfilling his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50330:11"/>of the honor he ſhould have in entring this Town. And though he comforted his Brother with this honor, yet himſelf ſtanding in the Waggon look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on no body, but held his Face continually down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>They were both put to the torture, but what they there confeſſed, is not well known; onely that <hi>Stenko</hi> did very much lament the death of his Brother, who by the command of <hi>Kneas Jurge Dolgeroek</hi> had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been hanged.</p>
            <p>His Brother <hi>Frolko</hi> behaving himſelf moſt pittifully under the torture, <hi>Stenko</hi> went about to comfort him again, and ſaid, That he muſt remember the good things he had enjoyed; that he had lived ſo long among his Friends with great credit and reputation, and had commanded thouſands; and therefore he was now to bear this hard fortune with patience.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ruſſes</hi> uſe this manner of Torture; they ſhave the Crown of the Head of a Malefactor, and drop cold Water upon it, which they ſay cauſeth very great pain. It is related, That when the Crown of <hi>Stenko,</hi> and his Brother was ſhaved, <hi>Stenko</hi> ſaid to his Brother, I have often heard, that none is ſhaved for a Prieſt, but he muſt be Learned; we are both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, and yet they do us the honor of ſhaving our Crown.</p>
            <p>Four days after that he was brought in, he was with his Brother carried to the place of Execution in the Cittadel. The Sentence of Death was read be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, wherein were expreſſed the Principal Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies he had committed. He ſeemed not at all concerned, and ſpoke not a word, but ſtooped. And when the Executioner was going to do his office, he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50330:12"/>croſſed himſelf ſeveral times, directing his face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a certain Church, called <hi>Pretſietſe Bogorodietſe Caſaneche;</hi> that is, <hi>The moſt Holy Mother of God of Caſan.</hi> And thereupon he bowed his head thrice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards three ſeveral places of the people aſſembled, ſaying, <hi>Prostie,</hi> that is, <hi>Forgive me.</hi> And preſently he was laid down between two Beams, and his Right Arm cut off to the Elbow, and his Left Leg to the Knee. After this, his Head was cut off with an Hatchet: All which was done with great ſpeed in a very ſhort time; and <hi>Stenko</hi> gave not the leaſt ſigh, nor ſhewed any ſign of ſenſe.</p>
            <p>His Brother coming to the place of Execution, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>That he had the Czar's word;</hi> a manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, when a perſon hath any ſecret to reveal, which is to be manifeſted to none, but to the great Czar alone. Being asked what it was, he ſaid, <hi>It was to be told to none but to the Czar.</hi> Whereupon he was reprieved; and they ſay, That he hath diſcovered the place of the Treaſure digged under Ground by his Brother <hi>Stenko.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the end of <hi>Stenko Razin;</hi> his Deputy <hi>Sjorte-Ous</hi> whom he had left to command in <hi>Astracan,</hi> is ſaid to have raiſed new commotions; putting to Death the Metropolite, and others that are contrary to his deſign. God Almighty give to the great Czar, <hi>Alexis Michaelewitz,</hi> the Victory over all his Enemies.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Arch. Angel,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 23/23. 1671.</date> on Board of the Ship, the Queen <hi>Eſther.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sentence">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50330:12"/>
            <head>The Sentence of Death read before <hi>STENKO RAZIN,</hi> on the Place of Execution. <hi>June</hi> 6. 1671.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Villain and Renegado Rebel <hi>Donsky-Coſack Stenko Razin,</hi> in the year 7175 <hi>alias</hi> 1667. aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning the fear of God, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting thy Duty and Oath, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou art bound to His Majeſty the great Czar <hi>Alexis Michaelowitz,</hi> Emperor and Defendor of the Greater and Leſſer, and the <hi>White Ruſſia,</hi> haſt Rebelled againſt His ſaid Majeſty; and having raiſed other <hi>Coſacks,</hi> haſt marched with them to the River <hi>Volga,</hi> there to act thy Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lainous Deſigns: And coming there, thou haſt done great miſchief to much people, taking the <hi>Naſaisky</hi> great Boats, laden with Salt-fiſh and Salt, belonging to the Patriarch, Cloyſters, and others: As alſo the Boats of many Merchants: Which Violence and Robbery, thou haſt acted as far as to the very Walls of <hi>Aſtracan.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50330:13"/>
            <p>Again, <hi>Thou Villain,</hi> haſt, betwixt <hi>Astracan</hi> and the <hi>Sorneiner,</hi> Robbed, Killed, and Thrown into the Water, the Waywood of the great Czar, <hi>Simon Bellemiſch,</hi> who was ſent to ſpeak with thee. The like villainy thou haſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon the Muſcovian Officer <hi>Suſover,</hi> that was likewiſe diſpatched to thee for the ſame end.</p>
            <p>When out of <hi>Astracan</hi> to the Town <hi>Jayck</hi> were ſent a Waywood, and two <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, with ſome Soldiers, to confer with you in an amicable way, and to perſwade you to deſiſt from your Villainous attempts, and to beg his Majeſties pardon, thou didſt hang both the Colonels, and betake thy ſelf with thy <hi>Coſacks</hi> to Sea from <hi>Jayck,</hi> and return from Sea into the <hi>Volga,</hi> ruining all places of Fiſhery, and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the habitations of the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou Villain</hi> haſt alſo been under the Town <hi>Tarchi,</hi> and haſt exceedingly endamaged the adjacent places; as alſo part of the Dominions of the King of <hi>Perſia.</hi> Being upon the <hi>Caſpian Sea</hi> thou didſt rob the Subjects of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and take away the Goods of Merchants, and their lives alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thou haſt alſo ruined ſeveral Towns in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and thereby cauſed great difference
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50330:13"/>between the Two Empires. Beſides, the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of <hi>Astracan</hi> upon thy orders, have killed their Colonel, and joyned themſelves to thee, doing great miſchief in many places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 7177 <hi>alias</hi> 1669. The Governor of <hi>Aſtracan, Kneas Jwan Simonewitz Proſorofsky</hi> ſent againſt you the Waywood <hi>Kneas Simon Leibof</hi> with His Majeſties Army, who had girt you all about; which <hi>thou Villain</hi> ſeeing, didſt diſpatch to that Waywood two of thy chief Confederates, praying in the name of all the <hi>Coſacks,</hi> that His Majeſty would pleaſe to pardon them, promiſing, That thereupon you would return home, and act no more miſchief, but ſerve the Czar with all Fidelity, without occaſioning any difference between His Majeſty and the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> as alſo without taking any thing upon the <hi>Volga,</hi> or the <hi>Caſpian Sea:</hi> Whereupon thoſe two <hi>Coſacks</hi> having taken an Oath in the name of the whole Body, and ſent to His Majeſty Seven perſons to implore his pardon (which was granted,) and your Forces being permitted to go with ſafety from <hi>Aſtracan,</hi> to the River <hi>Don,</hi> the place of your dwelling; notwithſtanding all this, <hi>thou Villain</hi> haſt forgot the Grace and Favor of the great Czar, and haſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50330:14"/>by the way exerciſed on the <hi>Volga,</hi> great rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, and coming to <hi>Tzaretſa,</hi> beaten the Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and committed enorm outrages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 7178 <hi>alias</hi> 1670. <hi>Thou Villain,</hi> together with thy Companions, forgetting the Fear of God, and deſerting the Holy Catholick Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Church, didſt, when you were upon the <hi>Don,</hi> ſpeak blaſphemous words againſt our Lord Chriſt, and prohibit to build Churches, and to perform Divine Service in thoſe that were in being; driving away all the Prieſts, and making ſuch people, as would marry, inſtead of practiſing the uſual Ceremonies of Marriage, to go round about a Tree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou Villain</hi> alſo, ſlighting the Grace of the great Czar vouchſafed to thee and thy Aſſociates, haſt afreſh rebelled againſt His Majeſty, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the River <hi>Volga,</hi> acting the like vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lainies, with Robbing and Killing as formerly, and particularly plundering and putting to death ſome honeſt antient <hi>Coſacks,</hi> that refuſed to joyn with you, and to approve of your Actions.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt likewiſe killed and caſt into the Water, thoſe that by the great Czar were ſent with Letters of Pardon to the Captain <hi>Cornelius
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50330:14"/>Jacolowitz</hi> and to other Donsky Coſſacks; and cauſed the reſt to be ſo beaten that they died of it.</p>
            <p>Marching from the River <hi>Don</hi> with thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Coſſacks, and coming to the Town of <hi>Tſaretza,</hi> thou haſt fraudulently perſwaded the people of that place, that the Czar's Army was coming to put them all to the ſword; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the contrary his Majeſties Army went to aſſiſt that Town againſt thee and thy villainous practices: upon which ungrounded perſwaſion the ſaid Town ſurrendred themſelves to thee, and received thee amongſt them. Entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, thou haſt put to the ſword the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Turgonova,</hi> and all thoſe Citizens, that would not be partakers in your villanies, and thrown them into the water; and thereupon thou didſt march out againſt the Army of the Great Czar, and by fraud rout the ſame, and didſt fling into the water their Colonel <hi>Jwan Lapatin,</hi> and their Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>Tedor Jeckschym,</hi> and others, after having put them to very great tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Beſides thou haſt taken away the Czar's Boats laden with Rye, and robbed many Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants; and after that thou didſt march to the Town <hi>Tzornojaar,</hi> and there kill the Governor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50330:15"/>
               <hi>Jwan Sergeof</hi> and all Officers, and many Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covian Soldiers.</p>
            <p>Coming before <hi>Aſtracan,</hi> thou madeſt ſome of thy villanous Coſſacks enter into it, and by them induce the Soldiers to deliver up the Town, and the Bojar and Waywood into thy hands: which was done accordingly; the Aſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can ſoldiers thereupon joyning themſelves with thee, and upon thy Orders pulling the Bojar, <hi>Kneas Jwan Simonowitz Proſorofsky,</hi> out of the Church, whom thou didſt caſt down headlong from a high Steeple, commanding alſo his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, together with many Noble-men, Officers, Soldiers, and Merchants, after grievous Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to be put to death; and robbing the Houſes of God, Churches and Monaſteries, as alſo the Czar's Treaſure, and many Houſes of the principal Citizens, and burning all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of State in the Chancery, with the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch ſcoffings as cannot be parallel'd.</p>
            <p>Moreover, thou haſt cauſed, without any ſhame, many Prieſts, Monks and Nuns to be ſtripp'd naked, and many other people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. Thou haſt alſo commanded moſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly to be beaten very many, to make them confeſs, where they had hid their Treaſure,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50330:15"/>without ſparing little children. Further, thou haſt put to death ſome of the chief Merchants of the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and many other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſtrangers, <hi>Perfians, Indians, Turkiſh, Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and <hi>Boucharen,</hi> who upon the account of Traffick, were at that time in <hi>Aſtracan;</hi> robbing them of their Goods, and occaſioning matter of diſcontent to the Great Chach of <hi>Perſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>thou Villain</hi> haſt been inſatiable of Blood, and continued to ſpill the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; and thou haſt not ſcrupled to hang up by their Leggs upon the Wall both the innocent Children of the Bojar, <hi>Kneas Jwan Simonowitz Proſorofsky,</hi> and after great Torture to worry the one, and ſo to beat the other, that thou thoughteſt he could not live. And thou haſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cauſed the Clerks, that ſerved the Great Czar, and would not conſent to thy deſigns, to be put to painful deaths, commanding them to be hanged up by their Ribs.</p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>Thou Villain,</hi> after having killed in <hi>Aſtracan</hi> many good people, haſt delivered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wives and their Daughters to be abuſed by your confederate miſcreants; commanding al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Prieſts that they ſhould marry none at
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50330:16"/>the Metropolitan's Order, ſcoffing at the Church of God, and the Ordinances of the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and annulling the Sacrament of Marriage, and throwing ſuch Prieſts as refuſed to comply with thee, into the water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou Villain</hi> haſt alſo robbed the Treaſure of the Great Czar in <hi>Aſtracan;</hi> and after an effuſion of much blood, thou didſt march out of that City to <hi>Tſarietza,</hi> and thence up the River to <hi>Tſaratof,</hi> whoſe Inhabitants ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred themſelves unto thee; and there thou didſt rob the Corn-Moneys of his Majeſty, and great ſtore of Proviſion, putting to death the Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wode <hi>Koeſmakoteſin</hi> and many Noble men.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Saratof, Thou Villain,</hi> perſiſting in thy malitious deſigns, didſt come to the Town <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marof,</hi> which alſo was ſurrendred to thee, and whence thou didſt carry away the Czar's Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, putting to the ſword the Governour <hi>Jwan Alſienofsky,</hi> and many Noble-men and Citizens, that would not take your part.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Samarof,</hi> thou Miſcreant didſt proceed to the Town <hi>Simbierske,</hi> to which thou laidſt a Siege, and tookſt it by ſtorm, doing much miſchief there. Thou didſt alſo ſend to many other Towns ſome of thy villanous Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50330:16"/>by falſe Writings bearing them in hand, that the Eldeſt Son of our Great Czar, of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious memory, our Czarawitz <hi>Alexis Alexewitz,</hi> Great Duke of the Greater, Leſſer and the White <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> was yet living, and that thou by Order of his Majeſty, waſt come to put to death as Traytors, all Bojars, Councellors, Noble men and Officers, being in his Majeſties ſervice: whereas, on the contrary, the ſaid Son of our Great Czar, departed this mortal life, and paſs'd into the everlaſting Reſt of Heaven; and that in his Pallace, in the preſence of his Lord Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the year 7178, <hi>alias</hi> 1670. the 17th of <hi>January;</hi> his Corps being buried in <hi>Moſco</hi> in the Cathedral of <hi>S. Michel,</hi> amongſt his Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the very next day after his death, likewiſe in the preſence of his Lord Father the Great Czar, and of the Lords the Patriarch of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Payſy,</hi> and the Patriarch of <hi>Moſco; Joſeph,</hi> and of many Metropolitans, Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, and Prieſts: which departure of our Lord <hi>Czarawitz</hi> of Glorious memory, is not only notorious here, but in other Kingdoms alſo. But <hi>Thou Traytor</hi> didſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe this with a deſigne to diſcompoſe the people, and to occaſion the ſhedding of innocent blood.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50330:17"/>
            <p>Thou haſt alſo craftily given out, as if the Monk <hi>Nikow</hi> was with thee; whereby thou haſt ſcandalized many; for this <hi>Nikow</hi> was, by the Order of the Great Czar, according to the condemnation of the Patriarch, depoſed from his Office, and ſent to <hi>Beelooſer</hi> into the Cloyſter <hi>Verapond,</hi> where he yet is.</p>
            <p>Moreover, thou didſt alſo like a <hi>Villain,</hi> ſend thy Aſſociats and Traytors into the Army of the Bojar <hi>Kneas Jurge Alexewitz Dolgoroeck,</hi> to intice them to joyn in Rebellion with thee: which deſigne yet, by the good providence of God, hath been fruſtrated.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Thou Villain,</hi> lying about the Town <hi>Simbierske,</hi> was't not able with all thy ſtorming and cheating to effect any thing; foraſmuch as by the goodneſs of God Almighty, and the aid of our bleſſed Lady the Mother of God, the comfort of the Chriſtians, and upon the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Holy Father and Wonder-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Sergius,</hi> and by the Military ſtrength, and the proſperity of our Great Czar <hi>Alexis Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalowitz,</hi> Great Duke of all the Greater, Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and the White <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> as alſo of the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Lord our Czarawitz and Great Duke <hi>Jwan Alexewitz;</hi> and likewiſe by the prudent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50330:17"/>and careful Conduct, and the valour of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery of our Great Czar; <hi>Thou Villain</hi> and <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> with thy Confederates and Abettors, haſt been, neer the Town <hi>Simbierske,</hi> and in many other places, diſcomfited, and with a few of thy company didſt then eſcape, and retreat down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>In many other places have the Inhabitants, upon thy villanous ſollicitations, rebelled, and kill'd their Governors, and thrown them into the water: And <hi>Thou Villain</hi> haſt joyned thy ſelf to the villany of thy Brother, and you to gether have fallen into divers Frontier-places, where you have ſhed much innocent blood, and done great miſchief.</p>
            <p>In which your divelliſh practiſes, you perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>Villains, Stenka</hi> and <hi>Frolko,</hi> together with your Companions, did contemn and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride the Church of God, not underſtanding the Grace of the moſt Holy Mother of God, the Hope of Chriſtians, and of the Holy Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worker <hi>Sargius;</hi> deſigning the ruine of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial City <hi>Moſed,</hi> and of the whole Moſcovian Empire.</p>
            <p>You, with all your adherents, went ſo far in your wickedneſs, that you refuſed to obey the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50330:18"/>Laws of our Great God, who is Glorious in Trinity, and ſlighted the Mother of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Hope of the Chriſtians; putting all your confidence in your divelliſh practiſes: In which villainous deſign you have been engaged ſince the year 7175 (1667.) unto the year 7179 (1671.) <hi>April</hi> 4th; during which time you have ſhed ſtore of innocent blood, without ſparing that of poor harmleſs young Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 4th of the year 7179. (1671.) through the great mercy of the Almighty, and by the wiſe Conduct and the valour of the Army of the Great Czar, <hi>Alexis Michalowitz, Thou Villain</hi> waſt taken priſoner, and haſt been brought to his Majeſty, and in the Examination and upon the Torture haſt confeſſed thy Crimes: For which thy abominable Attempts and practiſes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted agarnſt God Almighty, and againſt our Great Czar, <hi>Alexis Michalowitz,</hi> Great Duke and Defender of all the Greater, Leſſer, and the White <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> for thy Rebellion and Treaſon, and for the Ruine and Deſolation cauſed by thee to all <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> the Great Czar hath commanded, and the Bojars have aſſented, that thou ſhouldſt be condemned to be Quartered.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50330:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
